Hello and welcome to another tutorial from Moe City.
In this one I'm going to demonstrate how to generate automated subtitles for any videos
you want using Python.
To get started on this one first you will need to install this pip package called OpenAI
Whisper.
So this package allows us to create a transcription, English transcription for any video.
You can also use it to translate the language as well.
If you have a video that's in a different language and you want to create or generate
subtitles in English, you can also do that.
So this is the pip package website and you can pretty much scroll down and see exactly
how everything is laid out, what kind of dependencies do you need.
You might also need the package called FFMPEG.
And that's also required to read the video files or if you want to display the video
and audio files as well.
They do support a large array of different languages.
You can take a look at how well kind of stuff they actually support and using the package
is actually quite easy.
Let me just show you the code that I've been using to generate subtitles for my videos.
At the moment this is literally the code that I'm using.
So I'm using the first I'm just importing Whisper, Whisper utilities, import the get writer
function, then load the model I'm using the base model here.
If you go to the website you can see the different models that they use.
So you have base, I need base small medium large.
I'm using the base one because I had some of the videos that were quite long.
So I want to make sure that I get as accurate subtitle as possible.
For the audio file I'm simply passing in them before file that I have and I'll play
that for you in a minute.
For the result I'm basically saving the transcription of the audio file and I'm disabling the FFP16.
So my CPU doesn't support FFP16.
So I'm just disabling that so it runs the FP32 mode instead.
And then on the setting up the output directory here.
Now I need to save the files as a BTT file because that was one of the requirements for
you to me when I released my new course on there.
The didn't accept SRT files but if you need to say generate SRT files for your videos
you can also just change the BTT to SRT and it will generate SRT files as well.
Okay, so let's stick to the BTT one for now.
So it's just basically running the get writer function file type and the output directory.
Okay, basically we're just running this to transfer up the audio file and save the results.
Okay, so before we run this one let me just show you the video.
So this video is from my quiz maker app development course that I've recently released
on due to me.
So if I just play this one this is the assignment video I believe.
Hello and an application.
So right now the one saved on the computer.
So this is on when it's designed to challenge you in a way where you can take an existing
program and add four functionalities to the program to enhance its usability in the
long run.
Let me just show you guys.
As you can see there's no subtitles on the video currently.
So I just need to add a subtitle so I can add more accessibility to the course.
So I just need to do here right now is I'm just going to run this one.
As run depending on the size of the video your the time is going to take to transcribe
the entire project might take a while but this is only a three minute video so you shouldn't
take that long.
Right now the subtitle has been generated as you can see there's a dot VTT file on here.
So if I click on that.
You can see that he has transcribed or transcribe the whole video with the timestamps on
it.
And now mind you the transcription for the videos are not 100% all the time so you might
still need to edit the files a little bit.
I find it a lot easier to simply edit the files rather than generating the files myself.
Okay so let's play the video again and let's see the results of the subtitle.
Hello and welcome to this assignment.
So one of the issues you can see here is it's hello and welcome to this assignment.
This is all instead of four.
Right.
So I'm going to use the minor four uses which make our app development course which is
given.
And I click apply it gets applied to the image here.
Okay so imagine I want to use this image here to the quiz right now.
So I have the link for the image right there.
Okay.
And then I want to add that to the program.
I'll go to add image.
I can paste the link into the text box here and click apply.
Right.
And if I save this quiz with a random question which is going to create and check the quiz
here.
You can save onto my location as the images and files here are local.
This would enhance your own features and functions that apply to your own project.
Okay.
I think the subtitle results are really good.
And with this small minor tweaks I can pretty much use this subtitle file for my video.
So I really hope you found this one useful and you can generate your own subtitle for
your videos and you know it helps you in some way.
The link to my new course is in the description here.
If you find this video helpful please leave a like and subscribe to the channel and I
will see you on the next one.