In this video, I'll show you how to read from a file in Python.
The first thing we need to do is open the file.
You're going to say, file equals open.
My file is called file.txt.
So I put that right there.
And then I put R as the mode that I want to open this file
in that stands for read.
Now, if your file is done the same directory as your Python file,
then you need to put in the absolute path to this file.
So C, colon slash slash, et cetera, whatever the path is to it.
If it's in the same directory, you can just put the name of the file.
Now, to actually read from the file, what you do is the following, print,
and then file.readlines like that.
For readlines, we'll give you a list containing all of the lines in the file.
Once you're done with the file, you need to make sure you close it.
So file.close.
When I run this, notice we get all of the lines inside of the file.
We just read the file.
Another way to do this is simply with read.
If you use .read, notice you're going to get a string that contains all of the text
in the file, but not based on its lines.
Finally, a quick way that you can do this as well that avoids you having to close it.
So say with open file as file like that, then you can read the file inside of here.
Now, you no longer need to close it.
Let's run the code.
Notice everything works.
Hopefully you found this helpful.
If you did, follow for more.